Guide to the Philosophy of Science Association Records, 1959-2005 ASP.1992.02
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Philosophy of Science Association Records
1959-2005
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Philosophy of Science Association
ASP.1992.02
12.75 Linear Feet (10 Boxes)
The Philosophy of Science Association (PSA) Records document the professional engagements and administrative business of the Philosophy of Science Association, an organization founded in 1933 to further the study and discussion of subjects related to the philosophy of science. The Philosophy of Science Association promotes research, teaching, and free discussion of issues in the philosophy of science from diverse standpoints. To this end, the PSA engages in activities such as: the publishing of periodicals, essays and monographs; sponsoring conventions and meetings; and awarding prizes for distinguished work in the field.
Acquisition Information
Gift of the Philosophy of Science Association in 1992.
Scope and Content Notes
The Philosophy of Science Association Records contain records that document the administration of the Philosophy of Science Association between 1959-2005. The collection includes planning documents regarding the Association's Biennial meetings, governing board correspondence and election material, financial records, membership information and grants. Also included are article submissions, copyright documentation and correspondence regarding the Philosophy of Science journal, which was first published in 1934.
Access Restrictions
Access to Series XV. Subseries 7. Rejected Biennial Meeting Papers and Symposia Submissions and Series XVI.Journal Submission Files are restricted 75 years from date of submission.
Arrangement
The Philosophy of Science Association Records are arranged in 16 series:
Series I. Biennial Meetings
Series II. Related Professional Organizations
Series III. Copyright and Permissions for Publishing
Series IV. Offices and Officials
Series V. Journal Management
Series VI. Governing Board
Series VII. Travel Grants
Series VIII. Correspondence
Series IX. Election Files
Series X. Joint Conferences
Series XI. Financial Records
Series XII. Membership Information
Series XIII. Newsletters
Series XIV. Journal Issues
Series XV. Biennial Meeting Papers and Symposia Submissions
Series XVI. Journal Submission Files
History
Founded in 1933, the Philosophy of Science Association (PSA) promotes research, teaching, and free discussion of issues in the philosophy of science from diverse standpoints. To this end, the PSA engages in activities such as: the publishing of periodicals, essays and monographs; sponsoring conventions and meetings; and awarding prizes for distinguished work in the field.
The Philosophy of Science Association was first announced in the Journal of Philosophy, December 1933: "We welcome the first number of a new philosophical quarterly, entitled Philosophy of Science. It is the 'chief external expression' of the Philosophy of Science Association." (vol. 30, no. 25. p. 700) The first editorial board for the new journal was composed of William Malisoff (as editor), Eric T. Bell, Albert E. Blumberg, Rudolf Carnap, Morris R. Cohen, W. W. Cook, Herbert Feigl, K. S. Lashley, Henry Margenau, H. J. Muller, L. Susan Stebbing, Dirk J. Struik, and Alexander Weinstein. The first issue of Philosophy of Science appeared in January 1934, and was shepherded not just by the editorial board, but also by more than 40 other advisory board members, including P.W. Bridgman, R.A. Fischer, M. Polanyi, H. Reichenbach, George Sarton, E. A. Singer, jr., H. Urey, and E. Wigner.
Early activities of the PSA included co- sponsorship of the Fifth International Congress for the Unity of Science, held at Harvard in September 5-10, 1939. Other sponsors included the International Committee of the Congresses for the Unity of Science, the International Institute for the Unity of Science, the American Association for the Advancement of Science (AAAS), the Association for Symbolic Logic, and the American Philosophical Association. After World War II, the PSA began to meet annually at December AAAS meetings, in conjunction and cooperation with Section L (History and Philosophy of Science) of the AAAS. In addition to organizing symposia on philosophy of science at AAAS, the PSA began to conduct its business of governance at these meetings. It passed its first set of by-laws at the 1946 meeting, which would be revised in 1947, and then finally published in 1948 in Philosophy of Science.
According to its by-laws, the PSA was dedicated to "furthering of the study and discussion of the subject of philosophy of science, broadly interpreted, and the encouragement of practical consequences which may flow therefrom of benefit to scientists and philosophers in particular and to men of good will in general." (Phil. Sci. 1948, vol. 15, p. 176) In addition, the 1947 by- laws state that the PSA was to meet annually. For the next fifteen years, notices of the annual meetings were placed in "News and Notices" in Philosophy of Science every October for the meeting that was held in December, in conjunction with Section L of AAAS.
PSA president Adolf Grünbaum organized the first stand-alone biennial meeting of PSA in 1968, held in Pittsburgh, PA. This began the tradition of biennial meetings and became enshrined in PSA by-laws in 1970. The next meeting was held in Boston, MA in October 1970, and because of the death of Rudolf Carnap in September 1970, it was held in Carnap's honor. Those proceedings were published by the Boston Studies Series in Philosophy of Science (vol. VIII), edited by Roger Buck and Robert Cohen, and were the first published PSA proceedings.
Related Materials
Herbert Feigl Papers, 1916-1973, ASP.1997.01, Archives of Scientific Philosophy, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Rudolf Carnap Papers, 1905-1970, ASP.1974.01, Archives of Scientific Philosophy, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Hans Reichenbach Papers, 1884-1972, ASP.1973.01, Archives of Scientific Philosophy, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Ernest Nagel Papers, 1925-1985, ASP.2020.01, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Carl Gustav Hempel Papers, 1903-1997, ASP.1999.01, Archives of Scientific Philosophy, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
David L. Hull Papers, 1965-2004, ASP.2005.01, Archives of Scientific Philosophy, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Science -- Philosophy -- Societies, etc. -- History -- 20th century; Science -- Philosophy -- Congresses -- History -- 20th century; Science -- Philosophy -- Periodicals -- 20th century; Manuscripts for publication; Administrative records; Directories; Newsletters; Philosophy of Science Association -- Administration; Philosophy of Science Association. Biennial Meeting; Grünbaum, Adolf; Carnap, Rudolf, 1891-1970; American Association for the Advancement of Science; National Science Foundation (U.S.) -- Research grants; American Philosophical Association -- Administration
- Biennial Meetings, 1968-1996; I.
  Scope and Contents
  Biennial meetings series documents the Philosophy of Science's biennial meetings from 1968-1996. Files are labeled by meeting year and site and contain correspondence, financial planning documents, book display planning documents, program design and hotel information.
  - 1968 (Pittsburgh) Biennial Meeting Program (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1968 (Pittsburgh) First Biennial Meeting General (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1968-1994 Biennial Meetings Financial Summaries (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 1970 (Boston) Biennial Meeting Program (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 1970 (Boston) Second Biennial Meeting General (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 1972 (Lansing) Biennial Meeting Program (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 1972 (Lansing) Third Biennial Meeting General (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 1974 (South Bend) Biennial Meeting Program (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 1974 Fourth Biennial Meeting General (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 1974-1976 Biennial Meetings Book Displays (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - 1975-1976 (Chicago) Fifth Biennial Meeting- General (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - 1975-1979 San Francisco Jack Tar Hotel (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 1976 (Chicago) Biennial Meeting Program (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - 1976 (Chicago) Fifth Biennial Meeting General (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - 1978 (San Francisco) Biennial Meeting Program (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - 1978 (San Francisco) Program Committee (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - 1978 (San Francisco) Sixth Biennial Meeting (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - 1978 (San Francisco) Sixth Biennial Meeting Ads and Book Displays (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - 1980 (Toronto) Biennial Meeting Program Committee (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - 1980-1988 Biennial Meetings Book Exhibit- General (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - 1982 (Philadelphia) Bicentennial Meeting Program Committee (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - 1982 (Philadelphia) Biennial Meeting (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - 1982-1994 Conference Originals (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - 1984 (Chicago) Biennial Meeting (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - 1984 (Chicago) Biennial Meeting Book Display (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - 1984 (Chicago) Biennial Meeting Program (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - 1984 (Chicago) Conference Program Committee (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - 1988 (Evanston) Biennial Meeting (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - 1988 (Evanston) Biennial Meeting (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - 1988 (Evanston) Biennial Meeting Book Exhibits (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - 1988 (Evanston) Biennial Meeting Financial (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - 1988 (Evanston) Biennial Meeting Program (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - 1990 (Minneapolis) Biennial Meeting Book Exhibits (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - 1990 (Minneapolis) Biennial Meeting Financial (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - 1990 (Minneapolis) Biennial Meeting- General (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - 1990 (Minneapolis) Biennial Meeting- General (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - 1990 (Minneapolis) Biennial Meeting Program (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - 1992 (Chicago) Biennial Meeting Book Display (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - 1992 (Chicago) Biennial Meeting (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - 1992 (Chicago) Biennial Meeting Financial (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - 1992 (Chicago) Biennial Meeting Program (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - 1994 (Chicago) Biennial Meeting- General (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - 1994 (New Orleans) Biennial Meeting Program (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - 1995-1996 (Cleveland) Hotel Contract (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - 1996 (Cleveland) Program Office Letters (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Related Professional Organizations, 1972-1996; II.
  Related Professional Organizations series contains information about other professional scientific and philosophical organizations which the PSA engaged in cooperative and specialized project work between 1972-1996. Files are labeled by the name of the organization and includes the American Association for the Advancement of Science (AAAS), American Philosophical Association (APA), Institute for the Unity of Science, International Federation of Philosophical Societies, International Union for the History and Philosophy of Science, National Endowment for the Humanities, National Science Foundation and the Philosophy Journal Editor's Association.
  - American Association for the Advancement of Science (AAAS), 1972-1996; 1.
    The American Association for the Advancement of Science (AAAS) subseries contains memos and correspondence related to developments within the AAAS that were distributed to affiliate organizations, which included the Philosophy of Science Association. Information includes new publications, collaborative and learning opportunities and updates on leadership changes. Also included are meeting minutes of the AAAS board along with minutes from larger AAAS Coalition meetings between affiliate organizations. Files are arranged chronologically by year.
    - American Association for the Advancement of Science (AAAS), 1972 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - American Association for the Advancement of Science (AAAS), 1973 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - American Association for the Advancement of Science (AAAS), 1974 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - American Association for the Advancement of Science (AAAS), 1976 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - American Association for the Advancement of Science (AAAS), 1977 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - American Association for the Advancement of Science (AAAS), 1978 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - American Association for the Advancement of Science (AAAS), 1979 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - American Association for the Advancement of Science (AAAS), 1980 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - American Association for the Advancement of Science (AAAS), 1981 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - American Association for the Advancement of Science (AAAS), 1981 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - American Association for the Advancement of Science (AAAS), 1982 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - American Association for the Advancement of Science (AAAS), 1983 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - American Association for the Advancement of Science (AAAS), 1984 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - American Association for the Advancement of Science (AAAS), 1985 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - American Association for the Advancement of Science (AAAS), 1986 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - American Association for the Advancement of Science (AAAS), 1987 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - American Association for the Advancement of Science (AAAS), 1988-1989 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - American Association for the Advancement of Science (AAAS), 1990-1996 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - American Philosophical Association (APA), 1975-1989; 2.
    The American Philosophical Association (APA) subseries contains memos and correspondence related to collaboration between the APA and the Philosophy of Science Association. As an affiliate member, the APA often assisted the PSA in sharing employment opportunities for scientific philosophers, collaboration in journal publishing and joint cooperation in the development of the Conference of Philosophical Societies. Files are organized chronologically by year.
    - American Philosophical Association (APA), 1975-1976 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - American Philosophical Association (APA), 1978 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - American Philosophical Association (APA), 1978-1979 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - American Philosophical Association (APA), 1981 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - American Philosophical Association (APA), 1982-1983 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - American Philosophical Association (APA), 1984-1985 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - American Philosophical Association (APA), 1986-1987 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - American Philosophical Association (APA), 1988-1989 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - American Philosophical Association (APA), 1975-1976 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - American Philosophical Association (APA), 1977 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Association of Philosophy Journal Editors, 1972-1981; 8.
    The Association of Philosophy Journal Editors subseries contains minutes and correspondence created by the board Association of Philosophy Journal Editors Association, of which the Philosophy of Science Association was a member. Issues addressed in the work of the Association include proper editing and management of philosophical journals along with communication and collaborative efforts between Philosophical organizations to promote common professional standards in philosophical journal publishing.
    - Association of Philosophy Journal Editors, 1972-1973 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Association of Philosophy Journal Editors, 1974-1975 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Association of Philosophy Journal Editors, 1979-1981 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Institute for Unity of Science, 1976; 3.
    The Institute for the Unity of Science subseries contains correspondence, financial and legal documents regarding the incorporation of the Philosophy of Science association with the Institute for the Unity of Science (IUS), which was formed by Otto Neurath after the conclusion of the Eighth International Congress of Philosophy held in Prague in September of 1934. The IUS attempted to organize congresses and related activities that furthered the work of logical empricism developed by the Vienna Circle and engage in inter-scientific discussion groups with philosophers from around the world.
    - Institute for Unity of Science, 1974-1975 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Institute for Unity of Science, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - International Federation of Philosophical Societies, 1972-1973; 4.
    International Federation of Philosophical Societies: The International Federation of Philosophical Societies (IFPS) subseries contains correspondence regarding the Philosophy of Science Association's participation in the IFPS's efforts to serve as a coordinating agency for philosophical societies to promote international cooperation and host a quinquennial International Congress of Philosophy.
    - International Federation of Philosophical Societies, 1972-1973 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - International Union for the History and Philosophy of Science, 1967-1976; 5.
    The International Union for the History and Philosophy of Science subseries contains correspondence and memos regarding the Philosophy of Science Association's participation in the International Union for the History and Philosophy of Science. Information includes the PSA's affiliation and involvement in the group which included the selection of delegates from the PSA to attend the Union's General Assembly along with the PSA's work on the United States National Committee. The main activities of the Union are the two quadriennial congresses organized by the two divisions: the International Congress for History of Science and Technology (ICHST) and the Congress for Logic, Methodology and Philosophy of Science and Technology (CLMPST).
    - International Union for the History and Philosophy of Science, 1967-1971 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - International Union for the History and Philosophy of Science, 1974-1975 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - International Union for the History and Philosophy of Science, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - International Union for the History and Philosophy of Science, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - National Endowment for the Humanities, 1977-1979; 6.
    The National Endowment for the Humanities series includes correspondence that documents effort by the Philosophy of Science Association to secure NEH grant funding for research in scientific philosophy and to better promote NEH opportunities to PSA members through newsletter announcements and other correspondence. Files are arranged chronologically.
    - National Endowment for the Humanities, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - National Endowment for the Humanities, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - National Endowment for the Humanities, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - National Science Foundation, 1974-1995; 7.
    The National Science Foundation subseries includes grant applications and proposals for National Science Foundation travel and research grants applied for by by Philosophy of Science Association members. Files are organized by year.
    - National Science Foundation, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - National Science Foundation, 1975-1976 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - National Science Foundation, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - National Science Foundation, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - National Science Foundation, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - National Science Foundation, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - National Science Foundation, 1983-1987 (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - National Science Foundation, 1990-1995 (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - National Science Foundation Grant, 1982-1983 (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - National Science Foundation Grant Documentation, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - National Science Foundation Grant Documentation, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - National Science Foundation Grant Payment Info, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - National Science Foundation Travel Grant (Biennial Meeting), 1994 (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Joint Newsletters and Inter-Organizational Cooperation, 1976-1978; 8.
    Joint Newsletters subseries contains correspondence regarding the proposed development of a joint newsletter in cooperation between the PSA and the Society for the History of Technology (SHOT), Society for the Social Studies of Science (4S) and History and Sociology of Science (HSS). The subseries also includes correspondence held within the PSA about involvement and relationships with other organizations such as ACLS (American Council of Learned Societies), FISP (International Federation of Philosophical Societies) and The American Catholic Philosophical Association.
    - Joint Newsletter Correspondence, 1976-1978 (Box 3, Folder 48)
    - Inter-Organizational Cooperation (Ad Hoc), 1970-1974 (Box 3, Folder 49)
- Copyright and Permissions for Publishing, 1958-1994; III.
  Copyright and Permissions for Publishing series contains copyright and publishing release forms completed by authors in the Philosophy of Science journal between 1958-1994.
  - Copyright, 1958-1968 (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - Copyright, 1958-1968 (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - Copyright, 1958-1968 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Copyright, 1968-1973 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Copyright, 1968-1973 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Copyright, 1968-1973 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Copyright, 1974-1975 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Copyright, 1976-1977 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Copyright, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Copyright, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Copyright, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Copyright, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Copyright, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Copyright, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Copyright, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Copyright, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Copyright, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Copyright, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Copyright, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Copyright, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Copyright, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Copyright, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Copyright, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Copyright, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Copyright, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 23)
- Offices and Officials, 1970-1994; IV.
  Offices and Officials series contains administrative documents and correspondence kept by elected officers of the Philosophy of Science Association ranging from 1970-1994. Files are labeled by name of the officer and include PSA Presidents, Secretaries, Chairpersons and Journal Editors in Chief. Issues documented in the correspondence include the management of the Philosophy of Science Journal, communication with other professional scientific and philosophical organizations, and administrative issues in the PSA.
  - Asquith, Peter (Executive Secretary) Correspondence, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Burks, Arthur W. (President), 1975 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Butts, Robert (Editor in Chief), 1983-1990 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Cohen, Robert (President), 1983-1984 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Fine, Arthur (President), 1985-1990 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Giere, Ronald (President), 1992-1994 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Hesse, Mary (President), 1976-1979 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Hull, David (President), 1985-1986 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Kuhn, Thomas (President), 1989-1990 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - McMullin, Ernan (President), 1980-1984 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Rudner, Richard (Editor in Chief), 1972 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Rudner, Richard (Editor in Chief), 1973 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Rudner, Richard (Editor in Chief), 1974-1975 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Salmon, Merilee (Editor in Chief), 1992-1993 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Salmon, Merilee, (President), 1974 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Schaffner, Kenneth (Editor in Chief), 1976-1980 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Scheffler, Israel (President), 1973-1974 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - van Fraassen, Bas (President), 1990 (Box 4, Folder 41)
- Journal Management, 1970-1996; V.
  Journal Management series documentation of issues regarding the Philosophy of Science Journal between 1970 and 1996. Files include editorial board correspondence, Editor in Chief selection processes, journal inventories and issues and complaints raised about the contents of the journal.
  - Bobbs-Merrill Company Reprints, 1970-1973 (Box 4, Folder 42)